Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
计算机程序的构造和解释
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
翻译&&时间轴
张大伟
（DreamAndDead）
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
流 I
PROFESSOR: Well, last time Gerry really let the cat out of the bag.
上次Gerry教授揭晓了秘密
He introduced the idea of assignment.
他介绍了赋值的概念
Assignment and state.
赋值与状态
And as we started to see, the implications
正如我们所见
of introducing assignment and state into the language
将赋值和状态引入到语言中
are absolutely frightening.
后果相当糟糕
First of all, the substitution model of evaluation breaks down.
首先 代换模型不再能够描述求值过程了
And we have to use this much more complicated environment model
为了解释程序中语句的语义
this very mechanistic thing with diagrams,
我们不得不使用更复杂的环境模型
even to say what statements in the programming language mean.
也就是一种跟图表相关的非常机械的东西
And that's not a mere technical point.
并且 这不单纯地是一个技术上的问题
See, it's not that we had this particular substitution model and,
并不是因为代换模型在这里不怎么有效
well, it doesn't quite work, so we have to do something else.
所以我们得想些其它办法
It's that nothing like the substitution model can work.
而是代换模型这类机制都不再起效
Because suddenly, a variable
这是因为突然间 一个变量
is not just something that stands for a value.
不再是代表着一个值了
A variable now has to somehow specify a place
现在 变量用于指明一个位置
that holds a value.
一个存放值的位置
And the value that's in that place can change.
并且 这个位置的值可以发生改变
Or for instance, an expression like f of x
比如像 (F X) 这样的表达式
might have a side effect in it.
就可能含有副作用
So if we say f of x and it has some value,
如果我们执行 (F X) 得到某个值
and then later we say f of x again,
之后我们再次执行 (F X)
we might get a different value
可能因为求值的顺序
depending on the order.
而得到不同的值
So suddenly, we have to think not only about values
所以突然间 我们不能仅仅关注于值
but about time.
也要关注时序
And then things like pairs
序对也不仅仅
are no longer just their CARs and their CDRs.
只是它的CAR和CDR部分
A pair now is not quite its CAR and its CDR.
不是作为CAR部分和CDR部分的别称
It's rather its identity.
它也有自己的“身份”
So a pair has identity.
序对具有“身份”
It's an object.
它是一个对象
And two pairs that have the same CAR and CDR
两个具有相同CAR和CDR部分的序对
well, might be the same or different,
可能相同也可能不同
because suddenly we have to worry about sharing.
因为这之中可能存在“共享”
So all of these things enter as soon as we introduce assignment.
一引入赋值 这些就变成要考虑的问题了
See, this is a really far cry from where we started with substitution.
确实 这和我们说讲代换的时候差别悬殊
It's a technically harder way of looking at things
技术上来看 我们思考起来更加困难了
because we have to think more mechanistically about our programming language.
因为我们必须相当机械地思考程序语言
We can't just think about it as mathematics.
而不能仅仅用数学的方式来思考
It's philosophically harder,
我们也会遇到哲学问题
because suddenly there are all these funny issues
我们会被这样的问题所困扰：
what does it mean that something changes
事物的“改变”指的是什么？
or that two things are the same.
两个事物“同一”又如何判别？
And also, it's programming harder, because
并且 这也会给我们编程带来困扰
as Gerry showed last time,
正如 Sussman 教授上节课中讲的那样
there are all these bugs having to do with bad sequencing and aliasing
错误的表达式顺序和别名会产生BUG
that just don't exist in a language where we don't worry about objects.
这些问题在不需要考虑“对象”的语言中 是不存在的
Well, how'd we get into this mess?
我们是怎样陷入这样的困境的呢？
Remember what we did, the reason we got into this is
我们这样做的原因在于
because we were looking to build modular systems.
我们想要构造模块化的系统
We wanted to build systems that
我们想把系统划分为
that fall apart into chunks that seem natural.
数个自然组合的小块
So for instance,
举例来说
we want to take a random number generator
我们想要构造一个随机数发生器
and package up the state of that random number generator inside of it
把该发生器的内部状态封装起来
so that we can separate the idea of picking random numbers
这样我们就可以把选取随机数
from the general Monte Carlo strategy of estimating something
和用于估计的蒙特卡洛方法分离开来
and separate that from the particular way that you
进一步地把它同由 Ceraso 发明的
work with random numbers in that formula developed by Cesaro for pi.
求取 π 的公式分离开
And similarly,
相似地
when we go off and construct some models of things,
当我们着手构建事物的模型时
Ah, if we go off and model a system that we see in the real world,
我们去构建现实世界中事物的模型
we'd like our program to break into natural pieces,
我们想把程序组织成许多自然部分
pieces that mirror
这些部分就是
the parts of the system that we see in the real world.
现实事物的镜像
So for example, if we look at a digital circuit,
举个例子 对于一个数字电路
we say, gee,
我们会说
there's a circuit
这儿有一个电路
and it has a piece and it has another piece.
它有一个这样的元件 有一个那样的元件
And these different pieces sort of have identity.
这些元件都有不同的“身份”
They have state.
它们都有各自的状态
And the state sits on these wires.
状态附着在电路上
And we think of this piece as an object
我们认为这个元件是一个对象
that's different from that as an object.
这个元件又是另外一个不同的对象
And when we watch the system change,
当我们观察到系统发生了变化
we think about a signal coming in here
信号从这里传递过来
changing a state that might be here and going here
改变了可能存放在这里的状态 并向这里继续传播
and interacting with a state that might be stored there,
和一个存储在这里的状态交互
and so on and so on.
依此类推
So what we'd like is we'd like to build in the computer
我们想要在计算机中
systems that fall into pieces
构建模块化的系统
that fall into pieces that mirror our view of reality,
来反映我们对现实的看法
of the way that the actual systems we're modeling
根据我们正在建模的实际系统
seem to fall into pieces.
来划分子系统
Well,
然而
maybe the reason that building systems like this
构建像这样的系统
seems to introduce such technical complications
看起来带来了不少技术上的麻烦
has nothing to do with computers.
但这不是计算机造成的
See, maybe the real reason
或许 真正拖累我们
that we pay such a price to write programs
让我们花了那么大的功夫
that mirror our view of reality
才让程序反映现实世界的原因
is that we have the wrong view of reality.
是我们对现实世界的认识出了错
See, maybe time is just an illusion,
或许时间只是幻觉
and nothing ever changes.
什么都没有改变
See, for example, if I take this chalk,
就拿这个粉笔来说
and we say, gee, this is an object
我们认为它是一个对象
and it has a state.
它有自己的状态
At each moment it has a position and a velocity.
每时每刻 它都有一个位置和速度
And if we do something, that state can change.
如果我们做点什么 就可以改变它的状态
But if you studied any relativity, for instance,
但是你如果了解一点相对性的概念
you know that you don't think of the path of that chalk
你可能会认为粉笔的路径
as something that goes on instant by instant.
不是许多瞬时的离散点
It's more insightful to think of that whole chalk's existence
一种深刻的见解是把整个粉笔的存在看作
as a path in space-time.
时空中的路径
that's all splayed out.
全部都展开了
There aren't individual positions and velocities.
没有单独的位置与速度
There's just its unchanging existence in space-time.
在时空中的存在是不会发生改变的
Similarly, if we look at this electrical system,
相似地 如果我们来考察这个电气系统
if we imagine this electrical system is implementing
我们假设这个系统实现的是
sort of signal processing system,
某种信号处理系统
the signal processing engineer who put that thing together
把这些元件组合在一起的工程师
doesn't think of it as, well,
也不会把它们看作
at each instance there's a voltage coming in.
电压施加于每个独立的元件
And that translates into something.
转换成了某种东西
And that affects the state over here,
影响了这里的状态
which changes the state over here.
还改变了那里的状态
Nobody putting together a signal processing system thinks about it like that.
没有一个做信号处理的会这样想
Instead, you say there's this signal
相反 你会说
that's splayed out over time.
这里有一个在时间上伸展的信号
And if this is acting as a filter,
如果把这个看作一个滤波器
this whole thing transforms this whole thing
这个滤波器会把整个信号转化成
for some sort of other output.
不同的输出信号
You don't think of it as what's happening
你们不要把这些东西的状态
instant by instant as the state of these things.
想象成在许多瞬间接连发生
And somehow you think of this box as a whole thing,
我们把这个盒子看作一个整体
not as little pieces sending messages of state
而不是在一个特定的瞬间
to each other at particular instants.
互相发送状态信息的小系统
Well, today we're going to look at
今天我们将介绍
another way to decompose systems
另一种分解系统的方法
that's more like the signal processing engineer's view of the world
站在信号工程师的角度去看待现实世界
than it is like thinking about objects that communicate sending messages.
而不再认为对象间通过消息传递来通信
That's called stream processing.
它被称为“流处理”
And we're going to start by showing
我们打算展示
by showing how we can make our programs more uniform
如何让我们的程序变得更加统一
and see a lot more commonality
从中看到更多的共性
if we throw out of these programs
如果我们跳出这些程序
what you might say is a
我们会发现
inordinate concern with worrying about time.
我们对时序的考虑过度了
Let me start by comparing two procedures.
我们先来对比两个过程
The first one does this.
第一个是这样
We imagine that there's a tree.
想像这有一个树
Say there's a tree of integers.
一个由整数构成的树
It's a binary tree.
一个二叉树
Say 1.
这里是1
So it looks like this.
看起来就像这样
And there's integers in each of the nodes.
在每个节点上都有一个整数
And what we would like to compute is
我们想计算
for each odd number sitting here,
对这个树中所有的奇数
we'd like to find the square and then sum up all those squares.
计算它们的平方和
Well, that should be a familiar kind of thing.
我们对这类问题很熟悉
There's a recursive strategy for doing it.
有一种递归策略求解它
We look at each leaf, and either
观察每个叶子节点
it's going to contribute the square of the number if it's odd
如果是奇数我们就求它的平方 并加和
or 0 if it's even.
如果是偶数 就是0
And then recursively, we can say at each tree
递归地看 对于每一颗树 我们可以说
the sum of all of them is
它的平方和等于
the sum coming from the right branch and the left branch,
右子树的平方和 加上左子树的平方和
and recursively down through the nodes.
就这样沿着节点递归下去
And that's a familiar way of
我们已经很熟悉
thinking about programming.
这种程序设计的思考方式了
Let's actually look at that on the slide.
我们来幻灯片上看一下
We say to sum the odd squares in a tree,
为了计算一棵树中奇数的平方和
there's a test. Either it's a leaf node,
我们先要判断它是否是一个叶子节点
and we're going to check to see if it's an integer,
判断方法则是考察该节点是否为整数
and then either it's odd, in which we take the square, or else it's 0.
继而判断其奇偶性 以及是否应该求取平方并加和
And then the sum of the whole thing
然后 整个的解就是
is the sum coming from the left branch and the right branch.
左、右子树解的总和
OK, well, let me contrast that with a second problem.
好的 让我们再来和下面一个问题对比一下
Suppose I give you an integer n,
假如给你一个整数N
and then some function to compute of the first of each integer
再给定一个函数 把它应用在
1 through n.
1到N的每一个数上
And then I want to collect together in a list
我想把其中的一些值收集成一个表
all those function values that satisfy some property.
那些满足某种属性的函数值
That's a general kind of thing.
这是种一般性的说法
Let's say to be specific,
说得更具体一点
let's imagine that for each integer, k,
假设对于每个整数K
we're going to compute the k Fibonacci number.
计算第K个斐波那契数
And then we'll see which of those are odd
然后挑出其中的奇数
and assemble those into a list.
并把它们组成一个表
So here's a procedure that does that.
这个过程是这样的
Find the odd Fibonacci numbers among the first n.
寻找前N个斐波那契数中的奇数
And here is a standard loop the way we've been writing it.
这里是我们一直以来采用的循环方法
This is a recursion.
用到了递归
It's a loop on k,
以K为循环变量
and says if k is bigger than n, it's the empty list.
如果K大于N 返回空表
Otherwise we compute the k-th Fibonacci number,
否则计算第K个斐波那契数
call that f.
将其与变量F绑定
If it's odd, we CONS it on
如果是奇数 我们把它与
to the list starting with the next one.
从K+1计算得到的表相连接
And otherwise, we just take the next one.
否则 我们只取从K+1计算得到的结果
And this is the standard way we've been writing iterative loops.
这是迭代式循环的标准写法
And we start off calling that loop with 1.
我们以1为初值 启动这个循环
OK, so there are two procedures.
好的 就是这两个过程
Those procedures look very different.
它们看起来非常不同
They have very different structures.
完全不同的结构
Yet from a certain point of view,
然而 从一个特定的角度来看
those procedures are really doing very much the same thing.
两个过程做的事情是一样的
So if I was talking like a signal processing engineer,
如果我是一个信号处理工程师
what I might say
我可能会说
the first procedure enumerates the leaves of a tree.
第一个过程枚举了树的叶节点
And then we can think of a signal coming out of that, which is all the leaves.
可以认为是信号从一个全是叶节点的地方输出
We'll filter them to see which ones are odd,
我们想要过滤出其中的奇数
put them through some kind of filter.
把它们放入某种滤波器中
We'll then put them through a kind of transducer.
然后再把它们放入某种换能器
And for each one of those things, we'll take the square.
对每一个输出 我们对其取平方
And then we'll accumulate all of those.
最后把结果累积在一起
We'll accumulate them by sticking them together
我们以0为初值
with addition starting from 0.
通过加法把它们累积起来
That's the first program.
这是第一个程序
The second program,
对于第二个程序
I can describe in a very, very similar way.
我也可以用一种非常类似的方法来描述
I'll say, we'll enumerate
我们枚举
the numbers on this interval, for the interval 1 through n.
从1到N这个区间上的数
We'll, for each one,
对于每个数
compute the Fibonacci number,
计算对应的斐波那契数
put them through a transducer.
再放入一个换能器
We'll then take the result of that,
对于输出的结果
and we'll filter it for oddness.
再通过奇偶性进行过滤
And then we'll take those and put them into an accumulator.
最后 我们将这些放入累积函数
This time we'll build up a list,
这次我们要累积出一个表
so we'll accumulate with CONS
所以我们用CONS来做积累
starting from the empty list.
以空表为初始值
So this way of looking at the program
从这个角度来看
makes the two seem very, very similar.
这两个程序真的是太相似了
The problem is
问题在于
that that commonality is completely obscured
两个程序的写法导致
when we look at the procedures we wrote.
我们看不出其中的共性
Let's go back and look at some odd squares again,
再回头来看奇数平方和的问题
and say things like, where's the enumerator?
问题来了 哪个是枚举函数呢？
Where's the enumerator in this program?
程序中哪一部分有枚举的作用？
Well, it's not in one place.
枚举不是仅仅在一个地方表现出来的
It's a little bit in this leaf-node test,
在叶子节点的判断处存在一部分
which is going to stop.
在这个判断循环终止的地方
It's a little bit in the recursive structure of the thing itself.
也下面的递归结构中也有体现
Where's the accumulator?
累积函数又在哪儿呢？
The accumulator isn't in one place either.
它也不只在一个地方
It's partly in this 0 and partly in this plus.
它在 0 和 + 这两个地方分别体现出来
Right? It's not there as a thing that we can look at.
累积函数分散在过程的每个部分
Similarly, if we look at odd Fibs,
相似地 我们来观察奇数斐波那契数的例子
that's also, in some sense, an enumerator and an accumulator,
某种意义上 程序中也存在枚举函数与累积函数
but it looks very different.
但看起来非常不同
Because partly, the enumerator is here in this greater than sign in the test.
枚举部分地表现在(> k n)的判断中
And partly it's in this whole recursive structure in the loop,
部分地表现在下面的递归调用中
and the way that we call it.
还有就是启动循环的地方
And then similarly,
同样地
that's also mixed up in there with the accumulator,
其中也混杂了累积函数
which is partly over there
分别在这里
and partly over there.
和这里
So these very, very natural pieces,
所以这些非常自然的部分
these very natural boxes here don't appear in our programs.
我们之前画的那些方框在程序中完全看不出来
Because they're kind of mixed up.
因为它们混杂在一起了
The programs don't chop things up in the right way.
这些程序并没有很好地对问题进行切分
Going back to this fundamental principle of computer science
回到计算机科学的基本原理上来
that in order to control something,
为了控制某种东西
you need the name of it,
你需要它的名字
we don't really have control over thinking about things this way
我们还没有很好地掌握按这种方式来思考
because we don't have our hands in them explicitly.
这是因为我们没有显式地操作它们的手段
We don't have a good language for talking about them.
我们没有一门好的语言来讨论它们
Well, let's invent an appropriate language
好吧 我们来创造一门合适的语言
in which we can build these pieces.
用它来构建这些器件
The key to the language is these guys,
这种语言的关键在于
is what is these things I called signals?
这些叫作信号的东西到底是什么？
What are these things that are flying on the arrows between the boxes?
这些沿着箭头传递的是什么？
Well, those things
这些东西
are going to be data structures called streams.
是一种称作“流”的数据结构
That's going to be the key to inventing this language.
这也是发明这门语言的关键
What's a stream?
“流”是什么东西呢？
Well, a stream is, like anything else, a data abstraction.
和其它的东西一样 “流”是一种数据抽象
So I should tell you what its selectors and constructors are.
所以 我先说明它的选择函数与构造函数分别是什么
For a stream, we're going to have one constructor
对于流结构 我们有一个构造函数
that's called CONS-stream.
我们称其为CONS-STREAM
CONS-stream is going to put two things together
CONS-STREAM把两个事物放在一起
to form a thing called a stream.
构造出一个流
And then to extract things from the stream,
选择函数叫作HEAD
we're going to have a selector called the head of the stream.
用于从流中提取数据
So if I have a stream,
如果我有一个流
I can take its head
我可以取它的头部
or I can take its tail.
也可以取它的尾部
And remember, I have to tell you George's contract
我把和George的约定告诉你
to tell you what the axioms are that relate these.
让你们知道和这个相关的公理
And it's going to be for any x and y,
对于任何的X与Y
if I form the CONS-stream and take the head,
如果我把它们构造成一个流 并取其头部
the head of CONS-stream of x and y
(HEAD (CONS-STREAM X Y))
is going to be x
结果就是X
and the tail of CONS-stream of x and y is going to be y.
(TAIL (CONS-STREAM X Y)) = Y
So those are the constructor, two selectors for streams, and an axiom.
一个构造函数 两个选择函数 一个公理 就是这些
There's something fishy here.
这里有点可疑
So you might notice that these are exactly
你可能注意到了
the axioms for CONS, CAR, and CDR.
这些就是CONS、CAR和CDR的公理
So if I said instead of writing CONS-stream I wrote CONS
把CONS-STREAM换成CONS
and I said head was the CAR and tail was the CDR,
HEAD换成CAR TAIL换成CDR
those are exactly the axioms for pairs.
这些就是序对的公理
And in fact, there's another thing here.
事实上 还有另一个东西
We're going to have a thing called the-empty-stream
我们有一个叫THE-EMPTY-STREAM（空流）的东西
which is like the-empty-list.
像空表一样
So why am I introducing this terminology?
为什么我要引入这个术语呢？
Why don't I just keep talking about pairs and lists?
为什么我不继续使用序对与表呢？
Well, we'll see.
后面我们就知道了
For now, if you like, why don't you just pretend
暂时地 你们可以把术语“流”
that streams really are just a terminology for lists.
当作“表”的另一种说法
And we'll see in a little while why
一会儿我们就会知道 为什么
why we want to keep this extra abstraction layer
为什么我们需要这个额外的抽象层
and not just call them lists.
而不是继续把它看做表
OK, now that we have streams,
好的 有了流之后
we can start constructing the pieces of the language
我们就开始构建语言的部件了
to operate on streams.
用它来操作流
And there are a whole bunch of very useful things that we could start making.
我们可以构建出太多有用的东西了
For instance,
举例来说
we'll make our map box to take a stream, s,
我们构建MAP-STREAM 它的一个参数是流S
and a procedure,
以及一个过程
and to generate a new stream
它会生成一个新的流
which has as its elements
它的构成元素是
the procedure applied to all the successive elements of s.
将PROC应用到S的后续元素得到的结果
In fact, we've seen this before.
我们以前见过类似的
This is the procedure map that we did with lists.
就是以前在表上定义的MAP过程
And you see it's exactly map,
除了判断EMPTY-STREAM的部分
except we're testing for empty-stream.
完全就和MAP一样
Oh, I forgot to mention that.
哦 我忘了说了
Empty-stream is like the null test.
EMPTY-STREAM?就和NULL?差不多
So if it's empty, we generate the empty stream.
如果是空的 就返回一个空的流
Otherwise, we form a new stream
否则 就生成一个新的流
whose first element is the procedure applied to the head of the stream,
其第一个元素是PROC应用在流头部的结果
and whose rest
剩下的是
is gotten by mapping along with the procedure down the tail of the stream.
是MAP-STREAM对流尾部应用的结果
So that looks exactly like the map procedure we looked at before.
太像我们之前讲的MAP了
Here's another useful thing.
还有一个有用的函数
Filter, this is our filter box.
过滤函数 就是那个用来过滤的盒子
We're going to have a predicate and a stream.
以一个谓词和一个流作为参数
We're going to make a new stream
它将生成一个新的流
consists of all the elements of the original one that satisfy the predicate.
包含了在流S中所有
that satisfy the predicate.
满足谓词PRED的元素
That's case analysis.
这是一个“按条件分析语句”
When there's nothing in the stream,
如果流是空的
we return the empty stream.
就返回一个空流
We test the predicate on the head of the stream.
这里 用谓词来判断流的头元素
And if it's true,
如果为真
we add the head of the stream onto the result
就把这个元素
the result of filtering the tail of the stream.
和过滤流的尾元素得到的结果连接在一起
And otherwise, if that predicate was false,
否则 如果谓词判断为假
we just filter the tail of the stream.
就只返回过滤流的尾元素的结果
Right, so there's filter.
这就是过滤函数的原理
Let me run through a couple more rather quickly.
剩下的我快速过一遍
They're all in the book and you can look at them.
这些在书上都有 你们可以自己看
Let me just flash through.
来马上过一遍
Here's accumulate.
过程ACCUMULATE
Accumulate takes a way of combining things
ACCUMULATE的参数有：一个组合函数
an initial value in a stream
一个初始值和一个流
and sticks them all together.
将它们组合在一起
If the stream's empty, it's just the initial value.
如果流为空 返回初始值
Otherwise, we combine the head of the stream
否则 我们就把流头部
with the result of accumulating
和流尾部做ACCUMLATE的结果
the tail of the stream starting from the initial value.
组合起来
So that's what I'd use to add up everything in the stream.
这就是把流中元素累积在一起的方法
I'd accumulate with plus.
我会用加法来累积
How would I enumerate the leaves of a tree?
如何枚举树上的叶节点呢？
Well, if the tree is just a leaf itself,
如果这个树只是一个叶节点
I make something which only has that node in it.
我就构造一个只含有一个叶子节点的流
Otherwise, I append together the stuff of enumerating
否则的话 我就把
the left branch and the right branch.
左、右子树枚举的结果合并起来
And then append here is like the ordinary append on lists.
这里的APPEND-STREAM跟表上的APPEND类似
You can look at that.
再来看这个
That's analogous to the ordinary procedure for appending two lists.
这跟和合并两个表的过程太相似了
Ah... How would I enumerate an interval?
如何枚举一个区间呢？
This will take two integers, low and high,
它有两个参数 LOW和HIGH
and generate a stream of the integers going from low to high.
生成一个包含从LOW到HIGH的所有整数的流
And we can make a whole bunch of pieces.
由此 我们就可以构造一大堆的元件
So that's a little language of talking about streams.
这就是一门用来讨论流的小型语言
Once we have streams,
当我们有了流
we can build things for manipulating them.
就可以构建用于操作它们的过程
Again, we're making a language.
请注意 我们正在构建一门语言
And now we can start expressing things in this language.
现在 我们可以用这门语言来表达我们的想法
Here's our original procedure for summing the odd squares in a tree.
这个原始过程是累加树中奇数的平方的
And you'll notice it looks exactly now like the block diagram,
现在你会发现 它和那些方块图如出一辙
like the signal processing block diagram.
跟我们的信号处理方块图相吻合
So to sum the odd squares in a tree,
要计算树上奇数平方和
we enumerate the leaves of the tree.
先枚举树上的叶子节点
We filter that for oddness.
过滤出奇数
We map that for squareness.
再用平方来做映射
And we accumulate the result of that using addition, starting from 0.
最后用加法来累积 初始值是0
So we can see the pieces that we wanted.
这样我们就可以看到需要的片段
Similarly, the Fibonacci one,
类似地 斐波那契数的那个问题
how do we get the odd Fibs?
我们如何获得奇斐波那契数呢？
Well, we enumerate the interval from 1 to n,
从1到N枚举整数
we map along that,
再把FIB过程映射到上面
computing the Fibonacci of each one.
用来求取每项斐波那契数
We filter the result of those for oddness.
过滤出奇数的部分
And we accumulate all of that stuff
最后 以空表为初始值
using CONS starting from the empty-list.
用CONS将它们积累起来
OK, what's the advantage of this?
那么 这么做有什么优势呢？
Well, for one thing,
首先一点
we now have pieces that we can start mixing and matching.
我们现在有可以用来混搭的元件了
So for instance,
比如说
if I wanted to change this, if I wanted to ah...
如果我想把这里改变一下
compute the squares of the integers and then filter them,
想要计算整数的平方再进行过滤
all I need to do
我只需要
is pick up a standard piece like this
拿个像这里的MAP SQUARE这样的元件
it's a map square and put it in.
放进去就行了
Or if we wanted to do
又或者 如果我们想
this whole Fibonacci computation on the leaves of a tree
寻找树的叶节点对应的斐波那契数
rather than a sequence,
而不是一个序列所对应的
all I need to do
我只需要
is replace this enumerator with that one.
用这个枚举函数替换这个枚举函数
See, the advantage of this stream processing
看到了吧 流处理的优势就是
is that we're establishing--
我们建立了 --
this is one of the big themes of the course--
这也是本课中的一个重要主题 --
we're establishing conventional interfaces
我们建立了一个约定的接口
conventional interfaces that allow us to glue things together.
约定的接口可以让我们把事物粘合起来
Things like map and filter
像MAP和FILTER这样的东西
are a standard set of components
可以作为一组标准的组件
that we can start using for pasting together programs in all sorts of ways.
我们可以拿过来随意组合去构造程序
It allows us to see the commonality of programs.
它让我们看到了程序的共性
I just ought to mention,
虽然在这里
I've only showed you two procedures.
我只是给你们演示了两个过程而已
But let me emphasize
但是我要告诉你
that this way of putting things together
像这种用MAP、FILTER和ACCUMULATE
with maps, filters, and accumulators is very, very general.
组合起来构建程序的方式是非常非常通用的
It's the generate and test paradigm for programs.
这是一种“生成-测试”的编程范式
And as an example of that,
举例来看
Richard Waters, who was at MIT when he was a graduate student,
Richarc Waters -- MIT的一名硕士生
as part of his thesis research went and analyzed
他的学位论文的一部分调研了
a large chunk of the IBM scientific subroutine library,
IBM的科学计算程序库的主要代码
and discovered that about 60% of the programs in it
发现其中60%的程序
could be expressed exactly in terms using no more than what we've put here--
都可以用这样的范式来准确的表示出来
map, filter, and accumulate.
只用MAP、FILTER和ACCUMULATE
All right, let's take a break.
好 让我们休息一会
Questions?
有问题吗？
AUDIENCE: It seems like the essence of this whole thing
学生：整件事情的本质好像只是
is just that you have a very uniform, simple data structure
因为你用了一个统一、简单的数据结构
to work with, the stream.
也就是流
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：对
The essence is that you, again,
本质就是
it's this sense of conventional interfaces.
用这种约定的接口
So you can start putting a lot of things together.
因此你可以把许多东西组合起来
And the stream is as you say,
流只是 就像你说的
the uniform data structure that supports that.
只是一种可以支持那样操作的统一的数据结构而已
This is very much like APL, by the way.
顺便说下 这非常像APL
APL is very much the same idea,
APL有着非常相似的思想
except in APL, instead of this stream,
只是在APL中使用的不是流
you have arrays and vectors.
而是使用数组和向量
And a lot of the power of APL is exactly the same reason of the power of this.
而且APL的威力就在于此
OK, thank you.
好吧 谢谢
Let's take a break.
休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
流 I
All right.
好的
We've been looking at
我们已经见识过了
at ways of organizing computations using streams.
如何用流来组织计算过程
But what I want to do now is just show you two
但是现在我想要给你们再演示两个
somewhat more complicated examples of that.
更复杂的例子
Let's start by thinking about the following
我们先来考虑一下
kind of utility procedure that will come in useful.
这样一种有用的过程
Suppose I've got a stream.
假设我有一个流
And the elements of this stream are themselves streams.
流中的元素本身就是一个流
So the first thing might be 1, 2, 3.
一开始是1、2、3
So I've got a stream.
就是这样的一个流
And each element of the stream is itself a stream.
流中的元素也是一个流
And what I'd like to do is build a stream
而我想要构建出一个流
that sort of collects together all of the elements,
用来收集所有的元素
pulls all of the elements out of these sub-streams
把所有元素从子流中提取出来
and strings them all together in one thing.
最后把它们串接在一起
So just to show you the use of this language, how easy it is,
为了凸显使用这门语言多么简单
call that flatten.
我们来定义这个FLATTEN过程
And I can define to flatten this stream of streams.
FLATTEN过程的参数是由流构成的流
Well, what is that?
那么 具体定义是怎样的呢？
That's just an accumulation.
它只是一个累积
I want to accumulate using append,
我想用APPEND来做累积
by successively appending.
也就是不断地做APPEND
So I accumulate using append streams,
所以我用APPEND-STREAM做累积
starting with the-empty-stream down that stream of streams.
以THE-EMPTY-STREAM为初始值 累积这个流
OK, so there's an example of
这个例子告诉我们
how you can start using these higher order things
你可以使用这些高阶过程
to do some interesting operations.
来做一些有趣的运算
In fact, there's another useful thing that I want to do.
事实上 我还想定义另一个实用过程
I want to define a procedure called flat-map,
定义一个过程FLAT-MAP
flat map of some function and a stream.
它以一个过程和一个流为参数
And what this is going to do is s will be a stream of elements.
其中S是一个流
f is going to be a function
F是一个过程
for each element in the stream produces another stream.
它作用于流中的每个元素 并产生一个新的流
And what I want to do is take all of the elements and all of those streams
我想从这些流中取出所有的元素
and combine them together.
并把它们组合在一起
So that's just going to be the flatten of map f down s.
所以对应的代码就是 (FLATTEN (MAP F S))
Each time I apply f to an element of s,
每当我将F应用在S的某个元素上
I get a stream.
我得到了一个流
If I map it all the way down,
执行完这条MAP语句后
I get a stream of streams,
我得到了一个由流构成的流
and I'll flatten that.
再把它进行FLATTEN
Well, I want to use that to show you a
我想再使用这种方式
a new way to do a familiar kind of problem.
来解决另一个大家很熟悉的问题
The problem's going to be like a lot of problems you've seen,
这个问题和我们以前遇到过的许多问题一样
although maybe not this particular one.
只是有些变型
I'm going to give you an integer, n.
给定整数N
And the problem is going to be
我们的问题是
find all pairs and integers i and j,
找出所有的整数序对(I, J)
between 0 and i, with j less than i, up to n,
其中 0 < J < I <= N
such that i plus j is prime.
使得 I+J 是一个质数
So for example, if n equals 6,
如果N=6
let's make a little table here,
我在这儿画个小表格
i and j and i plus j.
表头是I、J和I+J
So for, say, i equals 2 and j equals 1, I'd get 3.
比如说I=2 J=1 那么I+J就是3
And for i equals 3, I could have j equals 2, and that would be 5.
然后I=3 J=2 那么I+J就是5
And 4 and 1 would be 5 and so on,
I=4 J=1 I+J=5也是一样的 等等
up until i goes to 6.
直到I到了6就终止了
And what I'd like to return is to produce a stream
我想要这个过程产生并返回这样的一个流
all the triples like this, let's say i, j, and i plus j.
就是像 (I, J, I+J) 这样的三元组组成的流
So for each n, I want to generate this stream.
对于每个整数N 我想得到一个这样流
OK, well, that's easy.
听起来很简单
Let's build it up.
我们做做看
We start like this.
先这样开始
We're going to say for each i, for each i
对于每一个整数 I
we're going to generate a stream.
生成一个流
For each i in the interval 1 through n,
对于I从1取到N
we're going to generate a stream.
每个I都生成一个流
What's that stream going to be?
这个流将会是什么样子？
We're going to start by generating all the pairs.
我们先生成所有的序对
So for each i, we're going to generate,
对于每个I 我们先生成
for each j in the interval 1 to i minus 1,
对于每个从1取到I-1的J
we'll generate the pair,
我们先生成序对
or the list with two elements i and j.
也就是只含有I和J的表
So we map along the interval,
因此我们对整个区间做映射
generating the pairs.
生成序对
And for each i, that generates a stream of pairs.
对于每个I 都生成一个序对流
And we flatmap it.
最后进行FLATMAP
Now we have all the pairs i and j,
这样我们就生成了所有的(I, J)序对
such that i is less than j.
其中I <= J
So that builds that.
就是这样
Now we're got to test them.
紧接着就是过滤
Well, we take that thing we just built, the flatmap,
我们对刚才FLATMAP得到的东西
and we filter it to see whether the i-- see, we had an i and a j.
我们以I -- 这里分别是 I 和 J
i was the first thing in the list,
I是表的第一个元素
j was the second thing in the list.
J是第二个
So we have a predicate which says in that list of two elements
我们用一个谓词来判断 表中的两个元素
is the sum of the CAR and the CDR prime.
也就是表的CAR部分与CDR部分之和 是否为质数
And we filter that collection of pairs we just built.
用这个谓词来过滤刚刚收集起来的表
So those are the pairs we want.
就得到了我们想要的表
Now we go ahead
然后我们继续
Now we go ahead and we take the result of that filter
把过滤得到的结果 再次进行MAP操作
we map along it, generating the list i and j and i plus j.
用来生成 I、J 和 I+J 构成的表
And that's our procedure prime-sum-pairs.
这就是过程 PRIME-SUM-PAIRS
Ok, and then just to flash it up, here's the whole procedure.
最后只需要过一遍 这就是整个过程
A map, a filter, a flatmap.
一个MAP、一个FILTER 以及一个FLATMAP
There's the whole thing,
所有的东西都在这里了
even though this isn't particularly readable.
尽管可读性不是那么好
It's just expanding that flatmap.
我们只是把中间过程展开了
So there's an example
这个例子
which illustrates the general point
向我们展示了
that nested loops
嵌套循环
in this procedure start looking like compositions of
在这个过程中 它看起来就像
flatmaps of flatmaps of flatmaps of maps and things.
各种嵌套的MAP和FLATMAP的组合
So not only can we enumerate individual things,
所以我们不仅仅可以枚举单个个体
but by using flatmaps,
通过使用FLATMAP
we can do what would correspond to nested loops in most other languages.
我们可以实现其它语言中的嵌套循环
Of course,
当然
it's pretty awful to keep writing these flatmaps of flatmaps of flatmaps.
重复写这些FLATMAP很烦人
Prime-sum-pairs you saw looked fairly complicated,
尽管PRIME-SUM-PAIRS其中单独的部分很容易
even though the individual pieces were easy.
但整体看起来还是十分复杂
So what you can do, if you like,
如果你愿意的话 可以
is introduced some syntactic sugar that's called collect.
引进一个叫COLLECT的语法糖衣
And collect is just an abbreviation
COLLECT只是一个缩写
for that nest of flatmaps and filters arranged in that particular way.
用来代表特定顺序的FLATMAP和FILTER操作
Here's prime-sum-pairs again, written using collect.
这里我们用COLLECT把PRIME-SUM-PAIRS写一遍
It says to find all those pairs, I'm going to collect together a result,
PRIME-SUM-PAIRS过程需要收集这样一个东西
which is the list i, j, and i plus j,
它的元素是形如(I, J, I+J)这样的表
that's going to be generated as i runs through the interval from 1 to n
而这将通过I从1取到N
and as j runs through the interval from 1 to i minus 1
同时J要从1取到I-1来产生
such that i plus j is prime.
并且要满足I+J是质数
So I'm not going to say what collect does in general.
课堂上我就不讲解如何定义COLLECT了
You can look at that by looking at it in the book.
书上面有
But pretty much, you can see that the pieces of this
不过你可以清楚地看到 这些代码片段
are the pieces of that original procedure I wrote.
就是我原先写的过程中的片段
And this collect is just some syntactic sugar
COLLECT过程只是一个语法糖衣
for automatically generating that nest of flatmaps and flatmaps.
用来自动生成嵌套FLATMAP
OK, well, let me do one more example
好的 我们再来看另一个例子
that shows you the same kind of thing.
也展示了同样的道理
Here's a very famous problem
这是一个非常著名的问题
that's used to illustrate a lot of so-called backtracking computer algorithms
经常用来演示所谓的“回溯”算法
This is the eight queens problem.
这就是“八皇后问题”
This is a chess board.
这是一个棋盘
And the eight queens problem says,
八皇后问题要求我们
find a way to put down eight queens on a chess board
找到一种将八个皇后放到棋盘上的摆法
so that no two are attacking each other.
使得任意的两个皇后不会相互攻击
And here's a particular solution to the eight queens problem.
这里给出了一个解法
So I have to make sure to put down queens
我需要保证摆放好后
no two are in the same row or the same column
任意两个皇后不在同一行或同一列上
or sit along the same diagonal.
也不在同一对角线上
Now, there's sort of a standard way of doing that.
有一个解决这个问题的标准解法
Well, first we need to do is
首先我们要做是
below the surface, at George's level.
进入底层 站在George的层面
We have to find some way to represent a board, and represent positions.
找到一种表示棋盘与位置的方式
And we'll not worry about that.
这个并不需要太担心
But let's assume that there's a predicate called safe.
假设我们有一个谓词SAFE?
And what safe is going to do
SAFE?判断的是
is going to say given that I have a bunch of queens down on the chess board,
假如一些皇后已经放在棋盘上
is it OK to put a queen in this particular spot?
在这个点再放置一个皇后是否是安全？
So safe is going to take a row and a column.
所以SAFE?的参数分别为ROW和COLUMN
That's going to be a place where I'm going to try and put down the next queen,
我将尝试把下一个皇后放在那个地方
and the rest of positions.
另外一个参数是剩下的位置
And what safe will say
SAFE?要判断的是
is given that I already have queens down in these positions,
在这些位置已经放置了皇后的情况下
is it safe to put another queen down
在这行这列放置皇后
in that row and that column?
是否安全
And let's not worry about that.
不用过分深究这个
That's George's problem. and it's not hard to write.
那是George的问题 也不难写出来
You just have to check whether this thing contains any things
只需要检测该行、该列
on that row or that column or in that diagonal.
以及对角线上是否有东西即可
Now, how would you organize the program given that?
那么 有了这个过程后 我们的程序该如何组织呢？
And there's sort of a traditional way to organize it
有一种传统的方式
called backtracking.
我们称为“回溯”
And it says, well, let's start off
首先让我们来考虑
let's think about all the ways of putting the first queen down
把第一个皇后放在第一列的
in the first column.
所有方式
There are eight ways.
有8种
Well, let's say try the first column.
先试下第一列
Try column 1, row 1.
第一行第一列
These branches are going to represent
每个分支都代表了
the possibilities at each level.
在每一个层次的可能解
So I'll try and put a queen down in the first column.
我试着把皇后放在第一列
And now given that it's in the first column,
现在 我在第一列放置好一个皇后以后
I'll try and put the next queen down in the first column.
我又尝试在第一列放置下一个皇后
That's no good, they're both...
并不成功 它们都……
I'll try and put the first queen,
我尝试把第一个皇后
the one in the first column, down in the first row.
把在第一列上的那个皇后 放在第一行
I'm sorry.
不好意思
And then given that, we'll put the next queen down in the first row.
放好后 我们再把下一个皇后放在第一行
And that's no good.
这不行
So I'll back up to here.
所以又回到这里
And I'll say,
然后再考虑
oh, can I put the first queen down in the second row?
我们把这个皇后放在第二行吗？
Well, that's no good.
然而也不行
Oh, can I put it down in the third row?
那么放在第三行呢？
Well, that's good.
这样可以
Well, now can I put the next queen down in the first column?
下一个皇后可以放在第一列吗？
Well, I can't visualize this chess board anymore,
我不能再画更多的棋盘了
but I think that's right.
但我先假设这个可行
And I try the next one.
我尝试下一个
And at each place, I go as far down this tree as I can.
在每一个地方 尽可能的沿着树往下
And I back up.
然后回退
If I get down to here and find no possibilities below there,
如果我从这里往下走 发现下面不可能有解
I back all the way up to here,
我就回溯到这里来
and now start again generating this sub-tree.
然后开始生成这个子树
And I sort of walk around.
我就像这样遍历
And finally, if I ever manage to get all the way down,
最后 一路求解下来
I've found a solution.
就会得到答案
So that's a typical sort of
这种典型的范式
paradigm that's used a lot in AI programming.
之前被广泛地使用在人工智能编程中
It's called backtracking search.
术语叫做 “回溯搜索”
And it's really unnecessary.
这真的没有必要
You saw me get confused when I was visualizing this thing.
你们也发现了 我在可视化这个过程时也犯了迷糊
And you sort of see the complication.
你们也看到了复杂程度
This is a complicated thing to say.
而且这种复杂还很难描述
Why is it complicated?
为什么会这样？
Its because somehow
这是因为
this program is too inordinately concerned with time.
这是因为这程序过分地关注于时间了
It's too much-- I try this one, and I try this one,
这之中太多 -- 先试试这个 再试试这个
and I go back to the last possibility.
再回到上一个可行的地方 -- 这种操作太多了
And that's a complicated thing.
这很复杂
If I stop worrying about time so much,
如果我们不再如此关注时间
then there's a much simpler way to describe this.
就有一个更简单的方式来描述
It says, let's imagine
让我们来想象一下
that I have in my hands
现在我有
the tree down to k minus 1 levels.
有一个高达K-1层的树
See, suppose I had in my hands all possible ways
假设我已经有了
to solve... to put down queens in the first k columns.
把皇后放在前K列的所有解法
Suppose I just had that.
假设是这样
Let's not worry about how we get it.
不要担心我是怎么得到的
Well, then, how do I extend that?
现在 如何扩充下去呢？
How do I find all possible ways to put down queens in the next column?
怎样找到在下一列中放皇后的所有可行方法？
It's really easy.
很简单
For each of these positions I have,
对于已有的位置
I enjoin, I think about putting down a queen in each row
我考虑把下一个皇后放在每一行上
to make the next thing.
来构建出下一步的棋局
And then for each one I put down,
然后 把所有放置的位置
I filter those by the ones that are safe.
用SAFE?进行过滤
So instead of thinking about
不像之前那样
this tree as generated step by step,
把这个树看做是逐步生成的
I say, suppose I had it all there.
我们假设所有的东西都生成好了
And to extend it from level k minus 1 to level k,
为了从K-1层扩展到K层
I just need to extend each thing in all possible ways
我只需要扩展所有可能的放置方法
and only keep the ones that are safe.
最后保留安全的排列
And that will give me the tree to level k.
就得到一个K层树的结果
And that's a recursive strategy
这是解决八皇后问题
for solving the eight queens problem.
的一个递归策略
All right, well, let's look at it.
好的 我们来看看
To solve the eight queens problem
我们编写子过程FILL-COLS
on a board of some specified size,
来解决在一个特定大小棋盘上的
we write a sub-procedure called fill-columns.
八皇后问题
Fill-columns is going to put down queens up through column k.
这个过程会把皇后放置到K个列中
And here's the pattern of the recursion.
这是递归的模式
I'm going to call fill-columns with the size eventually.
最后会以棋盘的大小为参数 调用FILL-COLS
So fill-columns says how to put down queens safely
FILL-COLS是用来说明
safely in the first k columns of this chess board
如何安全地把皇后放置在
with a size number of rows in it.
具有SIZE行的棋盘的前K列
If k is equal to 0,
如果K是0
well, then I don't have to put anything down.
就不用做什么
So my solution is just an empty chess board.
结果是一个空棋盘
Otherwise, I'm going to do some stuff.
否则就做点别的
And I'm going to use collect.
这里将要使用COLLECT
And here's the collect.
完整的代码在这里
I find all ways to put down queens in the first k minus 1 columns.
我找到了所有在前K-1列中放皇后的方法
And this was just what I set for.
这是我所假设的
Imagine I have this tree down to k minus 1 levels.
想像这棵树下降到K-1层
And then I find all ways of trying a row,
然后我尝试每一行
that's just each of the possible rows.
尝试每一个可行的行
They're size rows,
总共SIZE行
so that's enumerate interval.
这里枚举了所有行数
And now what I do is I collect together
现在要做的是
the new row I'm going to try and column k
把我将要尝试的新行和第K列
with the rest of the queens.
收集起来
I adjoin a position.
我邻接一个位置
This is George's problem.
这是George的问题了
An adjoined position is like safe.
实现ADJOIN-POSITION和SAFE?都是George的工作
It's a thing that takes a row
这个过程需要的参数有
and a column and the rest of the positions
ROW、COL以及REST-OF-POS
and makes a new position collection.
然后返回位置的集合
So I adjoin a position of a new row and a new column
我把新的行和列
to the rest of the queens,
和剩下的皇后邻接起来
where the rest of the queens
那些剩下的皇后
runs through all possible ways
会尝试所有的
of solving the problem in k minus 1 columns.
放置在K-1列中的可行解
And the new row runs through all possible rows
新的行遍历了所有的可能性
such that it was safe to put one there.
过滤出安全的位置
And that's the whole program.
这就是整个程序了
There's the whole procedure.
整个过程
Not only that, that doesn't just solve the eight queens problem,
它不仅找到了八皇后的问题的解
Right? It gives you all solutions to the eight queens problem.
它还给出了所有的解
When you're done, you have a stream.
运行结束之后 就得到一个流
And the elements of that stream are all possible ways of solving that problem.
流中的元素是所有的解
Why is that simpler?
为什么这个更简单一点呢？
Well, we threw away the whole idea that
我们完全没有把这个当做
is some process that happens in time with state.
按时间发生的、具有状态的过程
And we just said it's a whole collection of stuff.
我们只说 这是一些东西的集合
And that's why it's simpler.
这是它更加简单的原因
Right? We've changed our view.
我们已经转变了观念
Remember, that's where we started today.
还记得吗 这节课开始我们就讲过
We've changed our view of what it is we're trying to model.
我们转变了建模的观念
we stop modeling things that evolve in time
我们不再把事物看做按时间演进
have steps and have state.
也不再具有不同的阶段与状态
And instead, we're trying to model this global thing
取而代之的是 我们对全局进行建模
like the whole flight of the chalk,
我们关注粉笔的整个飞行过程
rather than its state at each instant.
而不是专注于每个瞬时状态
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
AUDIENCE: It looks to me like backtracking would be
学生：在我看来回溯会
searching for the first solution it can find,
搜索到它所能找到的第一个解
whereas this recursive search
而这个递归搜索
would be looking for all solutions.
会去寻找所有的解
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：是这样的
AUDIENCE: And it seems that
学生：但问题是
if you have a large enough area to search,
如果需要搜索的空间足够的大
that the second is going to become impossible.
第二种搜索方式就会变得不现实
PROFESSOR: OK, the answer to that question
教授：呃 这个问题其实是
is the whole rest of this lecture.
这一节课剩下的内容
It's exactly the right question.
这个问题很好
And without trying to anticipate the lecture too much,
先不要尝试去预知后面的课
you should start being suspicious at this point,
只是在现在 你们要保持谨慎
and exactly those kinds of suspicions. Isn't it?
这里确实有点奇怪 难道不是么？
It's wonderful, but isn't it so terribly inefficient?
尽管这个看起来不错 但是难道它不低效吗？
That's where we're going.
这是我们待会儿要解决的问题
So I won't answer now, but I'll answer later.
就让我们稍后来揭晓秘密吧
OK, let's take a break.
好吧 休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
I
Well, by now you should be starting to get suspicious.
你可能现在开始怀疑了
See, I've showed your this simple, elegant
我已经展示了这种简单而优雅的
of putting programs together,
组合程序的方法
very unlike these other traditional programs
这跟那些传统程序非常不同
that sum the odd squares
那些求奇数的平方和
or compute the odd Fibonacci numbers.
或者求奇数项斐波那契数之类的程序
Very unlike these programs that mix up
也不像那些混合了
the enumerator and the filter and the accumulator.
枚举函数、过滤函数和累积函数的程序
And by mixing it up,
通过把它们混合起来
we don't have all of these wonderful
通过这种混搭式的
conceptual advantages of these streams pieces,
组合程序的方法
these wonderful mix and match components
我们并没有获得
for putting together lots and lots of programs.
流式程序设计的理论优势
On the other hand,
另一方面
most of the programs you've seen look like these ugly ones.
你们所见过的大多数程序是那种丑陋的风格
Why's that?
为什么会这样？
Can it possibly be
难道计算机科学家们
that computer scientists are so obtuse
愚蠢得无以复加
that they don't notice
以至于他们没有注意到这个现象么？
that if you'd merely did this thing,
如果你仅仅只是做了这些事
then you can get this great programming elegance?
你就能让程序变得极其优雅么？
There's got to be a catch.
肯定有什么缺陷
And it's actually pretty easy to see what the catch is.
事实上这一缺陷也很容易发现
Let's think about the following problem.
我们来看看接下来的这个问题
Suppose I tell you to find the second prime
假设我让你去找
between 10,000 and 1 million,
1,000到1,000,000之间的第二个素数
or if your computer's larger,
如果你的计算机性能更强劲的话
say between 10,000 and 100 billion, or something.
或者可以去找10,000到100,000,000之间的
And you say, oh, that's easy.
你可能觉得这很容易
I can do that with a stream.
我可以用流来解决
All I do is I enumerate
我需要做的就是
the interval from 10,000 to 1 million.
从10,000枚举到1,000,000
So I get all those integers from 10,000 to 1 million.
我就获得了从10,000到1,000,000的所有整数
I filter them for prime-ness,
我过滤出所有的质数
so test all of them and see if they're prime.
也就是对这些数做素性检测
And I take the second element.
然后从中取出第二个元素
Right? That's the head of the tail.
也就是 TAIL的HEAD部分
OK? Well, that's clearly pretty ridiculous.
这显然是非常荒谬的
We'd not even have room in the machine
我们的机器没有这么大的空间
Right? To store the integers in the first place,
来存放这些整数
much less to test them.
更别说来测试它们了
And then I only want the second one.
而且我也只是取第二个数而已
See, the power of this traditional programming style
这种传统程序设计风格的威力
is exactly its weakness,
（虽然）也正是其弱点
that we're mixing up
这种程序设计风格
the enumerating and the testing and the accumulating.
混合了枚举、测试以及累积
Right? We sort of don't do it all.
我们不需要做全部的事
So by the actual... so the very thing
所以说 实际上这是这种
makes it conceptually ugly
概念上丑陋的风格
is the very thing that makes it efficient.
正是让它运行起来高效
Right? It's this mixing up.
就是像这样来混合
So it seems that all I've done this morning so far
我今天一早上所做的好像都是在
is just confuse you.
把你们搞糊涂一样
I showed you this wonderful way that programming might work,
我为你们展示了一种貌似可行的优雅程序设计方法
except that it doesn't.
但它却不可行
Well, here's where the wonderful thing happens.
但是 接下来就是见证奇迹的时刻
It turns out in this game
结果却是 这个游戏里
that we really can have our cake and eat it too.
我们真的可以得到蛋糕并吃掉它
And what I mean by that
我的意思是
is that we really can write stream programs
我们完全可以用流来组织程序
exactly like the ones I wrote
就像我之前编写的那样
and arrange things so that when the machine actually runs,
以至于当机器真正运行的时候
it's as efficient as running this traditional programming style
它可以和传统风格的程序一样高效
that mixes up the generation and the test.
那些混合了生成与测试的程序
Well, that sounds pretty magic.
听起来不可思议
The key to this
关键在就于
is that streams are not lists.
流不是表
We'll see this carefully in a second, but for now,
一会儿我们就会看到 但是现在
let's take a look at that slide again.
先让我们来看看幻灯片
The image you should have here
你们对这个
of this signal processing system
信号处理系统的印象是
is that what's going to happen
你们认为要发生的是
is there's sort of this box
在这类盒子中
that has the integers sitting in it.
事先产生好了整数
And there's this filter
这里有个过滤函数
that's connected to it and it's tugging on them.
它和那个盒子相连 并从中拉取东西
And then there's someone who's tugging on this stuff
这里还有人从这整个系统中
saying what comes out of the filter.
拉取东西
And the image you should have is that
你们应该这么来理解：
someone says, well, what's the first prime,
有人想要得到第一个质数
and tugs on this filter.
他从这个过滤函数这儿拉取
And the filter tugs on the integers.
FILTER从枚举函数中去拉取
And you look only at that much,
你只需要在固定范围内寻找
and then say, oh, I really wanted the second one.
然后从里面取出第二个数
What's the second prime?
第二个质数是多少？
And that no other computation
没有额外的计算
no computation gets done
只要你不去拉取东西
except when you tug on these things.
就不会产生进行额外计算
Let me try that again.
我来用实物演示一下
This is a little device.
这个小设备
This is a little stream machine
这是个小型的流机器
invented by Eric Grimson
这是Eric Grimson发明的
who's been teaching this course at MIT.
他也在MIT教这门课
And the image is ... here's a stream of stuff,
实际的流程是 -- 这里有某种流
like a whole bunch of the integers.
就像一串整数一样
And here's some processing elements.
这些是一些处理单元
And if, say, it's filter of filter of map, or something.
就像是FILTER、MAP之类的东西
And if I really tried to implement that with streams as lists,
如果我把流实现为表 来进行处理
what I'd say is, well, I've got this list of things,
我拥有的是一个表
and now I do the first filter.
现在 我先执行第一个过滤函数
So I sort of do all this processing.
我像这样完全处理
And I take this
针对这个流
and I process and I process and I process and I process.
不断地处理、处理、处理、处理
And now I'm got this new stream.
然后得到一个新的流
Right? Now I take that result in my hand someplace.
现在 我把得到的结果拿在我手中
And I put that through the second one.
然后把它放进第二个
And I process the whole thing.
又处理了全部的流
And there's this new stream.
得到一个新流
And then I take the result
然后我再把结果
and I put it all the way through this one the same way.
用相同的方式再次处理
That's what would happen to these stream programs
如果仅仅把流当做表的话
if streams were just lists.
计算的过程就是这样的
But in fact, streams aren't lists, they're streams.
但是事实上 流不是表 流就是流
And the image you should have is something a little bit more like this.
而你们应该这样来想像
I've got these gadgets connected up
我把这些小玩意连接起来
by this data that's flowing out of them.
数据在其中流动
And here's my original source of the streams.
这里是流的源头
It might be
它可能在
starting to generate the integers.
产生一些整数
And now, what happens if I want a result?
如果我想要拉取一个结果 会发生什么？
I tug on the end here.
我从尾部这里拉取
And this element says,
而这个单元会说
gee, I need some more data.
我需要更多的数据
So it's sort of, this one comes here and tugs on that one.
所以 它就到这个单元去拉取数据
And it says, gee, I need some more data.
它说：“我需要更多的数据”
And this one tugs on this thing,
然后这个又从下一个单元拉取
which might be a filter,
可能是一个过滤函数
and says, gee, I need some more data.
从它那里取得更多数据
And only as much of this
我在这一端拉取数据时
thing at the end here gets generated as I tugged.
只会生成这么多的数据
And only as much of this stuff goes through the processing units
我在另一端请求一定量的数据时
as I'm pulling on the end I need.
只有相当数量的数据被生成并处理
That's the image you should have
这就是你们需要知道的
of the difference between implementing
把流实现为表
what we're actually going to do
和流真实的工作方式
and if streams were lists.
的区别
Well, how do we make this thing?
那么 到底怎么来实现呢？
I hope you have the image.
知道了流的真实工作方式
The trick is how to make it.
构造流有什么窍门呢？
We want to arrange for a stream
我们想要把流组织成
to be a data structure
一种数据结构
that sorts of computes itself incrementally,
它能够增量式地计算自己
sort of on-demand data structure.
一种“按需”数据结构
Right? And the basic idea
基本思想在于
is again, one of the very basic ideas
再次强调 这是贯穿整个课程的
that we're seeing throughout the whole course.
几大基本思想之一
And that is
这就是
that there's not a firm distinction
数据与过程之间
between programs and data.
并没有绝对的界限
So what a stream is going to be
流会是这样的一种结构
is simultaneously this data structure that you think of,
它既是一种传统意义上的“数据结构”
like the stream of the leaves of this tree.
比如树的叶子结点组成的流
But at the same time,
但是同时
it's going to be a very clever procedure
它又是一种非常聪明的过程
that has the method of computing in it.
它包含了如何计算的方法
Well, let me try this.
好吧 实际来看一下
It's going to turn out
事实上
that we don't need any more mechanism.
我们不需要其它的机制
We already have everything we need
我们已经有了所需要的一切东西
simply from the fact
这是因为
that we know how to handle procedures as first-class objects.
我们已经能够 把过程当作第一级对象来处理了
Well, let's go back to the key.
来看看这个关键之处
The key is, remember, we had these operations.
关键在于 -- 回想一下 我们有这些运算
CONS-stream and head and tail.
CONS-STREAM、HEAD和TAIL
When I started, I said
刚开始的时候我说
you can think about this as CONS
你们可以把这个看作CONS
and think about this as CAR
把HEAD看作CAR
and think about that as CDR
把TAIL看作CDR
but it's not.
事实上没这么简单
Now, let's look at what they really are.
现在 来看看它们到底是什么
Well, CONS-stream of x and y
(CONS-STREAM X Y)
is going to be an abbreviation for the following thing.
是这个东西的缩写形式
CONS form a pair, ordinary CONS, of x to a thing called delay of y.
(CONS X (DELAY Y))
And before I explain that, let me go and write the rest.
我先把它们写完再来解释
The head of a stream
而(HEAD S)
is going to be just the CAR.
就是 (CAR S)
And the tail of a stream
而(TAIL S)
is going to be a thing called force the CDR of the stream.
则是(FORCE (CDR S))
Now let me explain this.
我来解释一下
Delay is going to be a special magic thing.
DELAY是一个特殊而神奇的东西
What delay does
DELAY所做是
is take an expression
取一个表达式
and produce a promise
然后产生一个PROMISE
to compute that expression when you ask for it.
在你有需要时 这个PROMISE会计算那个表达式
It doesn't do any computation here.
但在此时没有做任何计算
Just sort of... It just gives you a rain check.
只是一个延期的PROMISE
It produces a promise.
承诺要做这样的事
And CONS-stream says
CONS-STREAM所做的就是
I'm going to put together in a pair x
把X和一个计算Y的PROMISE
and a promise to compute y.
放在在一个序对里
Now, if I want the head,
如果我需要头部分
that's just the CAR that I put in the pair.
那么就是这个序对的CAR部分
And the key is that the tail is going to be--
关键在于 它的尾部分
force calls in that promise.
强制会调用该PROMISE
Force -- Tail says, well,
而TAIL会说
well, take that promise
好吧 取出该PROMISE
and now call in that promise.
然后调用该PROMISE
And then we compute that thing.
这才开始实际的计算
That's how this is going to work.
这就是它的实际工作方式
That's what CONS-stream, head, and tail really are.
这就是CONS-STREAM、HEAD和TAIL的真正定义
Now, let's see how this works.
具体演示一下
And we'll go through this fairly carefully. Let's --
我们小心翼翼地来审查一遍
We're going to see how this
现在从计算10,000到1,000,000中的
example of computing the second prime
第二个质数这个实例来看
right? between 10,000 and a million.
看看是怎么运行的
OK, so we start off and we have this expression.
好的 我们从这个表达式开始
Right? The second prime--
第二个质数就是
the head of the tail of the result of filtering for primality
就是(HEAD (TAIL (FILTER PRIME? ... )))
the integers between 10,000 and 1 million.
枚举的范围是(E-I 10000 1000000)
Now, what is that?
这是什么呢？
What that is,
那就是
that interval between 10,000 and 1 million,
枚举的这个10,000至1,000,000的区间
well, if you trace through enumerate interval,
如果你追踪这个枚举区间
there builds a CONS-stream.
会发现它构造了一个流
And the CONS-stream is
CONS-STREAM实际代换过来是
the CONS of 10,000
把10,000
to a promise to compute the integers between 10,001 and 1 million.
和一个计算10,001到1,000,000之间整数的PROMISE结合起来
Okay? So that's what this expression is.
这也就是上面这个表达式
Here I'm using the substitution model.
现在我使用代换模型
And we can use the substitution model
我们可以用代换模型的原因是
because we don't have side effects and state.
这里并没有涉及状态和副作用
Okay? So I have CONS of 10,000
所以我有10,000
to a promise to compute the rest of the integers.
和一个计算剩余整数构成的流
So only one integer, so far, got enumerated.
而到现在为止 只有一个整数被枚举了出来
Well, I'm going to filter that thing for primality.
然后过滤函数会对它做素性测试
Again, you go back and look at the filter code.
我们再来仔细看看过滤函数的代码
What the filter will first do is test the head.
过滤函数首先测试流的首部分
So in this case, the filter will test 10,000
这里 过滤函数会测试10,000
oh, 10,000's not prime.
然后输出：10,000不是质数
Therefore, what I have to do recursively
因此我只需要
is filter the tail.
递归地过滤尾部分
And what's the tail of it,
尾部分是什么呢？
well, that's the tail of this pair with a promise in it.
就是这个流的尾部分 -- 一个PROMISE
Tail now comes in and says,
我们进入到尾部分
well, I'm going to force that.
强制（计算）该PROMISE
I'm going to force that promise,
我强制计算该PROMISE
which means now I'm going to compute
这就意味着 我现在要
the integers between 10,001 and 1 million.
枚举10,001到1,000,000之间的整数
OK? So this filter now is looking at that.
现在 过滤函数处理的是这个东西
That enumerate itself,
这个枚举函数枚举了它自己
now we're back in the original enumerate situation.
我们又回到了最初那种枚举情况
The enumerate is
我们的枚举函数的
CONS of the first thing, 10,001,
首部分是整数10,001
onto a promise to compute the rest.
尾部分是计算剩余部分的PROMISE
So now the primality filter is going to go look at 10,001.
因此现在素性过滤函数将会测试10,001
It's going to decide if it likes that or not.
开始判断它是不是质数
It turns out 10,001 isn't prime.
结果10,001不是质数
So it'll force it again and again and again.
然后再不断地强制求值PROMISE
And finally, I think the first prime it hits is 10,009.
最后 我觉得它找到的第一个质数可能是10,009
And at that point, it'll stop.
它会在这个时候停止
And that will be the first prime,
这只是第一个质数
and then eventually, it'll need the second prime.
然而 我们需要的是第二个
So at that point, it will go again.
所以 这时它又启动了
So you see what happens is that
你会发现
no more gets generated
你需要多少
than you actually need.
它就只会生成多少
That enumerator is not going to generate any more integers
枚举函数生成整数的数量
than the filter asks it for
不会比过滤函数所要求的多
as it's pulling in things to check for primality.
因为它只是取一部分数来做素性测试
And the filter is not going to generate
过滤函数也不会生成
any more stuff than you ask it for,
比你的要求更多的东西
which is the head of the tail.
也就是尾部分的首部分
You see, what's happened is
你们看
we've put that mixing of generation and test
我们把计算机运行中实际进行的
into what actually happens in the computer,
生成与测试的过程 混合在了一起
even though
尽管
that's not apparently what's happening from looking at our programs.
我们的程序“看起来”显然不是这样
OK, well, that seemed easy.
看起来都很简单
All of this mechanism got put into this magic delay.
这种机制的神奇之处在于DELAY
So you're saying, gee, that must be where the magic is.
所以你也许会说 这全是因为DELAY很强大
But see there's no magic there either.
但其实并不是
You know what delay is.
DELAY其实很简单
Delay on some expression
(DELAY <EXP>)
is just an abbreviation for--
只是一个缩略表达
well, what's a promise to compute an expression?
它是-- 创建一个用于计算表达式的PROMISE
Lambda of nil, procedure of no arguments, which is that expression.
(LAMBDA () <EXP>) 这样的一个表达式
Right? That's what a procedure is.
这就是整个过程
It says I'm going to compute an expression.
这个PROMISE将要计算表达式<EXP>
What's force?
FORCE过程又是什么？
Right, how do I take up a promise?
如何处理这个PROMISE
Well, force of some procedure, a promise,
FROCE一个PROMISE -- 也就是某个过程
is just run it.
只是简单地运行它
Done.
就是这样
So there's no magic there at all.
所以这里并没有什么魔法
Well, what have we done?
总结一下 我们都干了些什么？
We said the old style,
我们说
traditional style of programming is more efficient.
传统的编程方式更有效
And the stream thing is more perspicacious.
而流程序却更加清晰
And we managed to make the stream procedures
我们设法用DELAY
run like the other procedures by using delay.
使流程序和其它过程一样高效
And the thing that delay did for us was to de-couple
DELAY所做的就是把
the apparent order of events in our programs
我们程序中 事件发生的逻辑顺序
from the actual order of events that happened in the machine.
和机器中 事件发生的实际顺序 解耦开来
That's really what delay is doing.
这是DELAY的实质作用
That's exactly the whole point.
也是全部的重点
We've given up, right, we've given up the idea
我们放弃了那种想法
that our procedures, as they run,
即程序的运行
or as we look at them,
或者源码的编排
mirror some clear notion of time.
反映了时间的明确概念
And by giving that up,
一旦放弃了这种想法
we give delay the freedom to arrange the order
我们能使用DELAY
of events in the computation the way it likes.
自由地安排计算顺序
That's the whole idea.
整个思想就是这样
We de-couple the apparent order
我们解耦了
of events in our programs
程序的逻辑顺序
from the actual order of events in the computer.
和其实际运行的顺序
OK, well there's one more detail.
对了 还有一个细节
It's just a technical detail,
一个技术性的细节
but it's actually an important one.
但是也非常重要
As you run through these recursive programs unwinding,
当你们运行这些递归程序的时候
you'll see a lot of things that look like
你会看到很多像是
tail of the tail of the tail.
(TAIL (TAIL (TAIL ... 这样的东西
Right. That's the kind of thing that would happen
如果流是通过嵌套的CONS构造起来的
as I go CONSing down a stream all the way.
就会出现这种情况
And if each time I'm doing that,
如果我每次都要执行一次
each time to compute a tail,
如果我每次都要计算TAIL
I evaluate a procedure
我对一个过程求值
which then has to go re-compute its tail,
这个过程又将重新计算它的TAIL
and re-compute its tail and recompute its tail each time,
它的TAIL又将重新计算TAIL的TAIL
you can see that's very inefficient
你们可以发现这非常低效
compared to just having a list where the elements are all there,
尤其是跟已经存放了所有元素的表相比
and I don't have to re-compute each tail every time I get the next tail.
因为那样 在取得下一个TAIL的时候不需要重新计算
So there's one little hack
因此 这里有一个小技巧
to slightly change the abbreviation, change what delay is
通过稍微修改DELAY的定义
and make it a thing which is-- I'll write it this way.
就可以让整件事变得 -- 我先写一下
Delay -- The actual implementation,
DELAY实际的实现是
delay is an abbreviation for this thing,
(DELAY <exp>)是这样一个表达式的简写
memo-proc of a procedure.
(MEMO-PROC (LAMBDA () <EXP>))
Memo-proc is a special thing that transforms a procedure.
MEMO-PROC是一个可以改变过程的特殊过程
What it does is it takes a procedure of no arguments
它接受一个无参过程
and it transforms it into a procedure
并把该过程变为
that'll only have to do its computation once.
只需要执行一次计算的过程
And what I mean by that is, you give it a procedure.
我们意思是 你给它一个过程
The result of memo-proc will be a new procedure,
MEMO-PROC返回一个新的过程
which the first time you call it,
当你首次调用这个新过程
will run the original procedure,
它会运行原始过程
remember what result it got,
并记下结果
and then from ever on after, when you call it,
从那之后 每次你再运行这个过程
it just won't have to do the computation.
就不用再计算了
It will have cached that result someplace.
它会把结果存储在一个地方
And here's an implementation of memo-proc.
可以这样来实现MEMO-PROC
Once you have the idea, it's easy to implement.
一旦你了解怎么做 实现就很容易了
Memo-proc is this little thing that has two little flags in there.
MEMO-PROC中有两个标记变量
It says, have I already been run?
ALREADY-RUN?用于记录是否运行过
And initially it says, no, I haven't already been run.
初始值是NIL 指示没运行过
And what was the result I got the last time I was run?
RESULT用于存储上一次计算的结果
So memo-proc takes a procedure called proc,
MEMO-PROC接收一个过程PROC
and it returns a new procedure of no arguments.
返回一个新的无参过程
Proc is supposed to be a procedure of no arguments.
PROC也是一个无参过程
And it says, oh, if I'm not already run,
它会判断 -- 如果没有运行过
then I'm going to do a sequence of things.
就进行一系列的运算
I'm going to compute proc,
先计算PROC
I'm going to save that.
然后存储它的值
I'm going to stash that in the variable result.
存储在变量RESULT中
I'm going to make a note to myself that I've already been run,
然后对ALREADY-RUN?赋值 提醒自己已经运行过了
and then I'll return the result.
最后返回RESULT
So that's if you compute it if it's not already run.
所以之前如果没运行过 就执行一次计算
If you call it and it's already been run, it just returns the result.
当你调用它 但已经运行过了 就直接返回结果
So that's a little clever hack called memoization.
这种聪明的小技巧被称作“记忆化”
And in this case,
这样的话
it short circuits having to re-compute the tail of the tail of the tail of the tail of the tail.
就不会重复的计算TAIL了
So there isn't even that kind of inefficiency.
不再那样的没效率了
And in fact, the streams
事实上 流式程序设计
will run with pretty much the same efficiency as the other programs precisely.
甚至和传统的那种程序一样有效
And remember, again, the whole idea of this
再强调一下 整个的思想在于
is that we've used
我们已经讲过
the fact that there's no really good dividing line
过程与数据之间
between procedures and data.
没有一个明确的分界线
We've written data structures that, in fact,
事实上 我们把数据结构组织得
are sort of like procedures.
像一个过程
And what that's allowed us to do
它使得我们能够
is take an example of a common control structure,
可以实现一种常见的控制结构
in this place iteration.
在本例中是迭代
And we've built a data structure
我们创建了一种数据结构
which, since itself is a procedure,
由于这种数据结构本身是一个过程
kind of has this iteration control structure in it.
它其中就可以有某种控制结构
And that's really what streams are.
这就是流的实质
OK, questions?
好 大家有什么问题吗？
AUDIENCE: Your description of tail-tail-tail,
学生：你刚才说(TAIL (TAIL (TAIL ...
if I understand it correctly,
如果我没理解错的话
force is actually execution of a procedure,
没有没有MEMO-PROC的话
if it's done without this memo-proc thing.
FORCE实际上执行了一个过程
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：是的
AUDIENCE: And you implied that memo-proc gets around that problem.
学生：你说使用那个MEMO-PROC就不会有那样的问题
Doesn't it only get around it if
这难道不需要保证
tail-tail-tail is always executing exactly the same--
(TAIL (TAIL (TAIL 每次的计算结构都是一致的么？
PROFESSOR: Oh, that's-- sure.
教授：哦 当然
AUDIENCE: I guess I missed that point.
学生：我可能是漏了什么知识点
PROFESSOR: Oh, sure. I mean the point is--  yeah.
教授：你说得很对 这里 --
Yeah, I mean I have to do a computation to get the answer.
首先 为了获得结果需要进行一次计算
But the point is, once I've found the tail of the stream,
关键在于 一旦得到 (TAIL STREAM)
to get the tail of the tail,
再计算 (TAIL (TAIL STREAM)) 的时候
I shouldn't have had to re-compute the first tail.
就不用再计算最内部的TAIL了
See, and if I didn't use memo-proc,
明白了吧 如果我没有用MEMO-PROC
that re-computation would have been done.
还要再计算一遍 (TAIL STREAM)
AUDIENCE: I understand now.
学生：明白了
AUDIENCE: In one of your examples, you mentioned that
学生：之前的例子中你提到过
we were able to use the substitution model
我们之所以可以使用代换模型
because there are no side effects.
是因为这里没有副作用
What if we had a signal processing unit--
如果我们的信号处理单元
if we had a side effect,
具有副作用
if we had a state?
具有内部状态
Could we still practically build the stream model?
我们还有效地构建流模型么？
PROFESSOR: Hum... Maybe, That's a hard question.
教授：可能吧 这是一个很困难的问题
I'm going to talk a little bit later about the places where
关于代换模型和副作用并不是很兼容这一点
where substitution and side effects don't really mix very well.
我以后会稍稍地讲解一下
But in general, I think the answer is
但大体来说 我认为
unless you're very careful,
除非你非常小心
any amount of side effect is going to mess up everything.
否则副作用会把一切弄得很糟糕
AUDIENCE: Sorry, I didn't quite understand the memo-proc operation. Uh...
学生：我不是很理解MEMO-PROC这个过程
When do you execute the lambda?
你是什么时候执行那个LAMBDA的？
In other words,
换句话说
when memo-proc is executed,
当MEMO-PROC执行的时候
just this lambda expression is being generated.
只生成了LAMBDA表达式
But it's not clear to me when it's executed.
但我不太清楚它是什么时候被执行的
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：好的
What memo-proc does-- remember,
MEMO-PROC所做的 --
the thing that's going into memo-proc, the thing proc,
MEMO-PROC的一个参数是PROC
is a procedure of no arguments.
一个没有参数的过程
And someday, you're going to call it.
某个时刻 你会调用它
Memo-proc translates that procedure
MEMO-PROC把该过程转化为
into another procedure of no arguments,
另一个无参过程
which someday you're going to call.
某个时刻你会调用到它
That's that lambda.
LAMBDA语句做的是这个
So here, where I initially built as my
所以在这里 我最初构造
I built as my tail of the stream,
构造流的TAIL的时候
say, this procedure of no arguments,
这里的这个无参过程
which someday I'll call.
会在之后的某个时刻调用
Instead, I'm going to have the tail of the stream be memo-proc of it,
相对应的 我要对(TAIL STREAM)调用MEMO-PROC
which someday I'll call.
以后我会调用生成的过程
So that lambda of nil,
所以这个无参的LAMBDA
that gets called when you call the memo-proc,
是当你在调用MEMO-PROC时调用的
when you call the result of that memo-proc,
当你调用MEMP-PROC返回的过程时
which would be ordinarily
也就会像通常的过程调用那样
when you would have called the original thing that you set it.
调用你最初设定的那个函数
AUDIENCE: OK, my ask is
学生：我想问的是
I had a feeling that when you call memo-proc,
当你调用MEMO-PROC的时候
you just return this lambda.
你返回了这个LAMBDA
PROFESSOR: That's right.
教授：是的
When you call memo-proc, you return the lambda.
你调用MEMO-PROC的时候 返回了一个LAMBDA
You never evaluate the expression at all,
直到你第一次需要执行它的时候
until the first time that you would have evaluated it.
你才去求值<EXP>
AUDIENCE: Do I understand it right
学生：我这样理解对吗？
you actually have to build the list up,
你构造了一个表
but the elements of the list don't get evaluated?
但表中的元素还没有被求值
The expressions don't get evaluated?
表达式没有被求值？
But at each stage, you actually are building a list.
但在每个阶段 你还是构造了一个表
PROFESSOR: That's-- I really should have said this.
教授：啊 我应该这样说
That's a really good point.
这个想法很好
No, it's not quite right.
但是 也不全对
See, cause what happens is this.
因为实际发生的事情是这样的
Let me draw this as pairs.
我先把这个画成序对
Suppose I'm going to make a big stream,
假设我要构造一个特别大的流
like enumerate interval,
比如枚举一段区间
1 through 1 billion.
从1到1,000,000,000
What that is, is a pair
这实际上是一个序对
a 1 and a promise.
由1和一个PROMISE组成
That's exactly what it is.
就是这样
Nothing got built up.
什么都没有构造
When I go and force this,
当我继续FORCE这个PROMISE
and see, what happens?
再来看看 会发生什么
Well, this thing is now also recursively a CONS.
这个东西现在就成为了一个递归CONS
So that this promise now is
所以这个PROMISE现在就变成了
the next thing, which is a 2 and a promise to do more.
一个2和做更多事情的PROMISE
And so on and so on and so on.
一直这样下去
So nothing gets built up until you walk down the stream.
直到你走完整个流才完整地构建了一个表
Because what's sitting here is not the list,
因为这个东西不是表
but a promise to generate the list.
只是一个生成表的PROMISE
And by promise, technically I mean procedure.
技术上来说 PROMISE就是一个过程
So it doesn't get built up.
因此并没有直接构造好一个表
Yeah, I should have said that before that.
我应该早点说的
OK. That you. Let's take a break.
好吧 就到这里 下课
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP